Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is דף ח, daf
chet, and we pick up literally at the very top of דף
ח, daf chet, אמר אביי. Amar Abaye. Now, the issue that had
come up yesterday was a statement by רב חסדא Rav Chisda revisiting
a question of whether you need something to be placed on a
space of four by four for it to be considered הנחה hanacha
or taken from a place in order to be considered עקירה. akira.
So after having a whole discussion of what constitutes רשות היחיד, reshut
hayachid, רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, and so on, we had רב חסדא's
Rav Chisda statement that if somebody threw an object
on somebody had a pole in the middle of a רשות היחיד,
reshut hayachid, let's say you had a flagpole surrounded by walls, and
you threw something from רשות הרבים reshut harabim and it landed on
top of the flagpole, you're חייב, chayav, even though there's not a
space of four by four. So what is this? This seems to
be that at least for רשות היחיד reshut hayachid and at least
for הנחה, hanacha, he doesn't require it. One way of understanding this
is what תוספות Tosafot said, which is that building on the idea
we had a few days ago that when one has a roof
in רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid, it's like it contains the space and
it's considered it's filled and it's like it's on the ground and
so on, here you would say it even without a roof. Since
we imagine that the walls of רשות היחיד reshut hayachid go all
the way up and this is contained within the walls, then it
doesn't have to be on the ground or on a space four
by four; in the רשות היחיד reshut hayachid is enough. Okay, so
now let's actually pick up, maybe just go back a little bit,
three lines on the bottom of ז עמוד ב zayin amud bet
where the גמרא Gemara wants to connect this to a statement of
רבי Rebbe we also saw in that earlier discussion of a space
of four by four. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, three
lines from the bottom of ז עמוד ב: zayin amud bet: לימא
רב חסדא דאמר כרבי? Lema Rav Chisda d'amar keRebbe? Maybe רב חסדא,
Rav Chisda, who is saying that it doesn't have to be on
a place four by four, again at least not in רשות היחיד,
reshut hayachid, is saying like רבי? Rebbe? דתניא, Detanya, we taught in
the ברייתא: Baraita: זרק ונח על גבי זיז כלשהו. Zarak venach al
gabi ziz kolshehu. Somebody threw, again, something presumably in רשות הרבים reshut
harabim and it landed on a tiny protrusion—we're assuming this is a
little protrusion in a רשות reshus, היחיד—רבי מחייב וחכמים פטורין. רבי Rebbe
says you have transgressed, presumably again because it's in, at least minimally
because it's in רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid maybe even more, but again,
let's keep the parameters the same, assume it's at least in רשות
היחיד. reshut hayachid, You do not—it's
even if it's on only on a tiny little ledge, you have
transgressed, and חכמים chachamim say you're exempt. And now in the parentheses,
which some take out but spell out the implications: אלמא לא בעינן
מקום ארבע על ארבע. Alman lo ba'inan makom arba al arba. You
see that you do not need a space of four by four,
again, maybe in no cases or at least minimally in a case
of רשות היחיד reshut hayachid. when it's coming to rest in a
רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid So that seems to be the same point
of רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. So let's see what אביי Abaye says.
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, said אביי: Abaye: ברשות היחיד דכולי עלמא לא
פליגי דרב חסדא. Bireshut hayachid d'chulei alma lo peligi d'Rav Chisda. You
know what? Fine. If it were in a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid.
like you've described it, even the חכמים chachamim who disagree with רבי
Rebbe in that ברייתא Baraita would agree. Really? Everybody would agree with
רב חסדא Rav Chisda that in רשות היחיד reshut hayachid you do
not need a space of four by four. Now that's a pretty
shocking change
considering that, you know, we had a whole סוגיא sugya at the
beginning of the, you know, a week ago or half a week
ago that was so much about who can be the person who
says you don't need four by four. Here אביי Abaye is asserting
that at least when it comes to a רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid
you do not need a space of four by four, at least
when it comes to הנחה. hanacha. Remember we said עקירה akira might
demand more. So אביי Abaye says, "I'm willing to say that with
when הנחה hanacha in רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid, everybody would agree with
רב חסדא Rav Chisda you don't need four by four." So then
what is this debate about throwing something and landing on a little
protrusion? אלא הכא באילן העומד ברשות היחיד ונופו נוטה לרשות הרבים. Ella
hacha be'ilan ha'omed bireshut hayachid venofo noteh lereshut harabim.
We're talking about a case where the tree is standing in רשות
היחיד reshut hayachid, but the branch goes into the רשות הרבים. reshut
harabim. וזרק ונח על נופו. Vezarak venach al nofo.
You're in רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, you threw it four אמות, amot,
let's say, maybe, whatever, anyway you threw it and it landed on
a branch of a tree, but the trunk of the tree is
in the רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid So what is the story there?
דרבי סבר, DeRebbe savar, רבי Rebbe holds, סבר אמרינן שדין נופו בתר
עיקרו, savar amrinan shadin nofo batar ikaro, you throw the branch towards
the trunk or towards the root, ורבנן סברי לא אמרינן שדין נופו
בתר עיקרו. v'Rabbanan savri lo amrinan shadin nofo batar ikaro. The רבנן
Rabbanan say you do not say this. Now, what is at stake
here? What's going on? The fact that the גמרא Gemara says—I really
have to start bringing markers because we're going to... we need diagrams
for this stuff—but anyway, the fact that the גמרא Gemara says that
the case is the tree is in רשות היחיד reshut hayachid. and
the branch is going into רשות הרבים reshut harabim obviously suggests that
the question we're going to be asking is: Where is the location
of something on the branch? If the branch is in רשות הרבים,
reshut harabim, right, I mean this comes up all the time in
property disputes, right? My tree that's planted in my property, again, the
branch is overhanging on your property, do you have a right
to... What do you do if the trunk is in one space
and the branch overreaches into another space? And something lands on a
branch. Where is that object considered to be? Is it considered to
be where the branch is or where the trunk is? That is
but certainly without a doubt the simplest way of interpreting אביי. Abaye.
אביי Abaye says look, when something is in a רשות היחיד, reshut
hayachid we could say against what we were saying a few days
ago, that at least when it comes to rest in רשות היחיד,
Reshut HaYachid, you do not need the space of four by four
to transgress. And here it fell on a branch and that little
branch is not four by four. So what's the debate of רבי
Rebbi and the רבנן? Rabbanan? The debate is where is it? In
a רשות היחיד Reshut HaYachid, or in a רשות הרבים? Reshut HaRabim?
Its branch is in רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabim but the trunk is
in רשות היחיד. Reshut HaYachid Now you presumably could transgress either way.
You threw it four אמות Amot in a רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabim
and it landed on the branch. So it could be carrying in
a רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabim or if the branch is considered רשות
היחיד Reshut HaYachid. it could be that you carried from רשות הרבים
Reshut HaRabim to רשות היחיד. Reshut HaYachid But here's the difference. If
it's considered in רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabim and it's on the branch,
it's not in a space four by four, you're exempt. In רשות
הרבים Reshut HaRabim it would have to land on a space four
by four. If however we consider the object on the branch to
be in רשות היחיד Reshut HaYachid. because that's where the trunk is,
then you threw the object into a רשות היחיד Reshut HaYachid and
it doesn't have to be on a space of four by four.
Okay so you understand there could be cases where even without the
four by four this question is relevant. Let's say you threw it
two feet in a רשות הרבים, Reshut HaRabim, two אמות, Amot, and
it landed on the branch. If it's a רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabim
you haven't done anything wrong. But if the branch is considered to
be in the רשות היחיד Reshut HaYachid then you've carried into the
רשות היחיד. Reshut HaYachid So this is a question that can be
asked in general and by the way it is asked in general.
There are a number of גמרות Gemarot that raise the question of
something, a tree whose trunk is in one place and branches in
another place, where is that considered to be? For example, I'll just
give you one colorful example, somebody is running to an ערי מקלט
Arei Miklat and the גואל הדם Goel HaDam is running after him
to kill him okay and he jumps into a branch of a
tree that the trunk of which is in the ערי מקלט Arei
Miklat but the branch of which is outside the ערי מקלט. Arei
Miklat. Where is the person? In the ערי מקלט Arei Miklat or
not in the ערי מקלט? Arei Miklat? Okay, so this is a
general question and here says אביי Abaye that's what's going on. Everybody
could agree with רב חסדא Rav Chisda that in a רשות היחיד
Reshut HaYachid. you do not need four by four but here the
question is it's the object landed on a branch in the רשות
הרבים Reshut HaRabim but the trunk is רשות היחיד. Reshut HaYachid If
it's in a רשות היחיד Reshut HaYachid. you carried into רשות היחיד
Reshut HaYachid and you don't need four by four. If it's on
the branch maybe you carried four אמות Amot in רשות הרבים Reshut
HaRabim but it's still רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabim and you're not חייב
chayav because the branch is not four by four. That is the
way תוספות Tosafot understands that's clearly the simple sense. I'll just mention
that what רש״י Rashi says is doesn't fit the words at all,
doesn't fit the emphasis of trunk in one place branch in another.
רש״י Rashi says the real question is the branch isn't four by
four but because it's connected to the trunk does the trunk give
weight you know or give significance to the branch that it's as
if it's four by four? So according to רש״י, Rashi, well fine,
according to רש״י Rashi which is certainly not the פשט pshat of
the גמרא Gemara because of the distinction A of רשות היחיד Reshut
HaYachid רשות הרבים, Reshut HaRabim, B because it says do you throw
the branch after the trunk? It does not say do you throw
the trunk after the branch? But רש״י Rashi somehow just makes this
a very sort of blander question about does the trunk give weight
to the branch but again the simple sense is as we've been
saying.
Sort of like what we had with the four by four? Yeah
considered as if it's a you know four by four.
Yeah yeah well this is a re-quoting of that. Okay so now
we that is the end of that discussion about רב חסדא Rav
Chisda and a גמרא Gemara that we had seen earlier when we
did the four by four discussion. Now we continue with a new
topic which also is about like רשות היחיד Reshut HaYachid רשות הרבים
Reshut HaRabim all these issues about carrying. And let's take a look
I really should have brought a marker for this. All right we'll
have to do
without. אמר אביי... Amar Abaye... Let me get them for you. Yeah
do
you
have any markers here?
Do you want a black marker?
Oh
yeah does it dry erase?
It's no if it's...
No I don't know I think it's permanent.
It's not the one you...
Yeah permanent I don't think so. Thank you. Good
to remember. All right anyway what... I take these
serious. All right we'll go on. We'll work with that. Okay אמר
אביי, Amar Abaye, said אביי. Abaye. זרק כוורת לרשות הרבים. Zarak Keveret
l'Reshut HaRabim. You don't also... Give me that sheet of paper maybe
I'll draw on that piece of paper here. Is there a blank
side on the other... Yeah all right here we'll do give me
your marker Bobby we'll do the best as we can. So אמר
אביי, Amar Abaye, said אביי. Abaye. זרק כוורת לרשות הרבים Zarak Keveret
l'Reshut HaRabim גבוהה יוד ואינה רחבה ו׳ gevoha yud v'einah rechava vav
חייב. chayav. You threw a... All right you... Thank you. You threw
a hive. Now this might have been literally a hive it might
be some type of a vessel. So that's in the shape of
a beehive, whatever. Let's say it's a beehive. You threw it into
רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. It is ten טפחים tefachim high but it
is not six טפחים tefachim wide.
Wait,
wait, חייב, chayav, you are חייב. chayav. ורחב ו' פטור, Ve-rachav vav
patur, if it is six טפחים tefachim wide, you are exempt. What
is this about? Let's map this down. Okay, here is your beehive,
okay? Remember geometry? You remember sort of what were they called, cylinders?
You know, you're going to have to figure out the volume of
the cylinder. I'm just teasing. Not so. Okay, here's your beehive, okay?
It's ten טפחים tefachim high. So the question is maybe it's going
to be a רשות היחיד. Reshut HaYachid Now it's six טפחים tefachim
wide. Now a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid. needs to be four טפח
tefach by four טפח, tefach, right? Now that is not just one
direction. It has to be a four טפח tefach by four טפח
tefach square, right? In order for this to be a רשות היחיד,
reshut hayachid it would have to have the area of four טפח
tefach by four טפח, tefach, which means that if it's not a
square but a circle, what's it going to have to have a
diameter of? Remember your geometry? No one? Well, it's going to have
to be a diameter of about, what's the diameter of that? What
is that? Four, four, what is the line, the diagonal? Four times
the square root of two. Thank you. Okay, this is four times
the square root of two, which is approximately 1.4, okay? So four
times 1.4 is 5.6. So, really אביי Abaye should have said 5.6,
he said six, רש"י Rashi says he was rounding, whatever, it's not
precise, it's got to be 5.6. So, if this is 5.6, or
we'll say approximately six across, okay, then this is a רשות היחיד.
reshut hayachid, It's ten high, it's four by four square, it's hollow,
so it's got walls on the inside, right? So this beehive is
a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. If, however, it is not ten טפחים
tefachim high or less than six, actually less than 5.6, then it
is not a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid.
Joyce, would you just tell me in English what you just said?
This is a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid.
This is a beehive, it's ten טפחים, tefachim, a טפח tefach is
a handbreadth.
No, I understand. When you say רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid.
רשות היחיד reshut hayachid, is private domain. Okay, so it would have,
if it has ten טפחים, tefachim, it has walls on the inside,
if it's got a square area of four by four, meaning it
has to have four in each direction, which means the diameter of
approximately six, then the inside of the beehive is a private domain.
If it's smaller than that, either shorter or not as wide, then
the inside of the beehive is not a private domain. Okay, so
let's, what does it matter? It matters like this. As רש"י Rashi
said, this is the way רש"י Rashi explains it, I'll tell you
in a minute how תוספות Tosafot explains it, it's a slight variation.
The תורה Torah only obligates you for throwing objects. It doesn't obligate
you for throwing domains, okay? Or for moving, for carrying. You know,
you carry in a domain, you don't carry a domain. So, you
know, I mean, you could imagine something, I mean, it might seem
absurd, you could imagine an easier case. I mean, let's say a
guy is, you know, carrying like, I don't know, one of those
portable סוכות sukkot on his back or something like that, you know.
Now, of course you could say, well, if it's being transferred it's
an object even though it's also, but this is what רש"י Rashi
says. If it fits the parameters of a domain, it's a domain,
it's not an object. So therefore what's the הלכה? halacha? Let's read
it again.
Joyce, we also talked about a tent, you could easily carry a
tent.
Yeah, but if it's folded, then it doesn't have, but it would
have to be open, open, right, an open tent. You could imagine
that. That's true. Okay, so anyway, if you threw this beehive, אמר
אביי, Amar Abaye, let's read that again. You threw this beehive, זרק
כוורת לרשות הרבים, zarak kaveret li-reshut ha-rabim, you threw it into a
public domain, let's say four אמות amot in a public domain, גבוה
י' ואינה רחבה ו', gavoha yud ve-eina rechava vav, so if it's
ten high but not six wide, again, six is a little imprecise,
but it means it's not wide enough so it's not yet the
parameters of a private domain, of רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid חייב, chayav,
you're obligated cause you carry, you threw or you carried an object.
ורחב ו', Verachav vav, once it's six wide, again, really 5.6, then
פטור, patur, you're exempt. Then what you've done is you've carried a
domain, not an object. Okay, now תוספות Tosafot says, that's רש"י's Rashi
explanation, you have to carry objects not domains.
What תוספות Tosafot says is slightly different. What תוספות Tosafot says is
the reason you're exempt is, says תוספות, Tosafot, what you did is
you carried this from a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid, and you threw
this beehive from a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid into the public domain.
So here's the story. The beehive when it lands is a רשות
היחיד. reshut hayachid So you threw this object from רשות היחיד reshut
hayachid. into where? It landed in רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, but it
became a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid So תוספות Tosafot says the reason
you're exempt is not because it as an object is not an
object, because when it landed it defined its space as רשות היחיד
reshut hayachid. and therefore you carried from רשות היחיד reshut hayachid to
a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid Whereas if it's smaller than that, then
when it landed. It’s not a new domain and it fell into
a רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabbim. So תוספות Tosfos says the issue here
is not that the object you're not חייב chayav if it's defined
as a רשות, reshus. the issue is is that you didn't place
it into a רשות הרבים.
Reshus Harabbim. Wait, shouldn't you be פטור? pattur?
No.
Why not? It’s in... I guess your question would be if you,
I don't know, if people trample on it or not trample on
it, I suppose you're right. I mean, if maybe as it landed
in רשות הרבים Reshus Harabbim in a way that people wouldn't trample
on it, would avoid it, then maybe then maybe that would be
true, but maybe we'll get into that.
I imagine most people would avoid it.
It’s an interesting question, quite תוספות. Tosfos. Okay, that’s an interesting point.
All right, but that's that's what the גמרא Gemara says. So either
way, once it's רשות היחיד reshut hayachid. you're exempt, either because of
the object or because of where it landed. Now the גמרא Gemara
says like this, רב Rav says, comes along רבא Rava and says,
אפילו אינה רחבה ו' פטור, Afilu eina rechava vav pattur, even if
it's not six wide, you could be exempt. Why? Isn't it an
object then? מאי טעמא? Mai taama? אי אפשר לקרומי של קנה שלא
יעלו למעלה מעשרה. Ee efshar lekromei shel kaneh shelo yaalu lemala measara.
Now, אביי Abaye says, ah, I've got a technical point.
This is landed in a רשות הרבים, Reshus Harabbim, right?
Here's your רשות הרבים Reshus Harabbim road that it landed.
It's ten טפחים tfachim high. But you know what? It's a beehive.
It's a beehive, if it's got little twigs, you know, that sort
of extend up. So these little parts of the twigs go higher
than ten טפחים, tfachim, but you'll remember that רשות הרבים Reshus Harabbim
only goes up to ten טפחים. tfachim. So part of the object
is outside of the רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabbim. And therefore, since the
entire object is not in רשות הרבים, Reshus Harabbim, you are exempt.
Remember we had a case before, like a a scroll rolled away
from you and you were holding onto part of the scroll in
another domain? If part of the object is in another domain, you're
exempt. Presumably אביי Abaye feels those little twigs are not significant. It's
not a real part of the object as true. But רבא Rava
says even those little twigs if they go higher than ten טפחים,
tfachim, the whole object is not in רשות הרבים, Reshus Harabbim, which
is a very interesting principle, which means that you could never be
חייב chayav for carrying something more than three feet high,
as soon as you put it down in רשות הרבים, Reshus Harabbim,
part of it is higher than the רשות הרבים.
Reshus Harabbim. Yes, it matters if the actual bees are part...
no, no, no.
Beehive is just something that... one at one time or could be.
Right, exactly. The beehive is just is just an example. It's not
relevant to how it's...
you'd say like שדר נופו בה? shadar nofo bah? Well, that’s maybe...
well, אביי Abaye would presumably say that the twigs are insignificant. Now,
so that's what רבא Rava says. Now, כפה על פיה, Kafa al
piha, that's if the mouth of the hive was towards the heaven.
However, let's say the mouth of it was towards the ground. שבעה
ומשהו חייב שבעה ומחצה פטור. Shiva umashehu chayav shiva umechetza pattur. In
that case, you don't go by ten, you go by seven. Why?
Because in that case, if you've got the mouth of it facing
the ground, okay, so here's your beehive, and here is the opening,
the mouth is on the bottom, okay? This is the floor, okay?
And here's the bottom of your רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabbim. So here's
the thing: when it's within three טפחים, tfachim, we're going to say
it's like it's already connected to the ground. We're going to say
לבוד lavud when it's within three טפחים. tfachim. Okay, because the the
hollow is facing the ground, you can consider this to already have
created within three טפחים tfachim to already be connected and be a
wall, right? If the if the floor was facing the ground, you
don't say לבוד lavud extend a wall because you're not looking at
the continuation of a wall, you're looking at a floor. But here
you're looking at the wall and you're extending the wall. So you
understand why it matters whether it's face up or face down. If
it's face down, you only have the floor, so maybe you could
say like the floor's on the ground, but you can't extend the
wall. Because here you have the open wall and within three טפחים
tfachim you can imagine it as if it's extended. So in this
case he says the following. If it's seven and a little bit,
okay, which means it's seven here and then the little bit gets
me within three טפחים, tfachim, okay, so it just
as it gets within the three טפחים, tfachim, now you're going to
have now it's going to become ten, then you're חייב. chayav. Now
you also... I'm sorry... then you are... excuse me, I got the
wording backwards. שבעה ומשהו, Shiva umashehu, let's do that again. שבעה ומשהו
חייב. Shiva umashehu chayav. You're חייב. chayav. Why?
Because... why isn't that a case of זורק רשות zorek reshus according
to רבא? Rava? Hold on, let me check this just... let me
double check.
Oh, oh, right, right, right. I'm sorry, I'm sorry, because רש"י Rashi
says that this is a case of...
רש"י Rashi says this is a case where it is not six
wide. Where it is, I don't know, call it five or close.
Okay, so if it's only if it's not six wide according to
רש"י, Rashi, right, if it's not six wide, it's an object, it's
not a רשות. reshus. It had to be six wide in order
to be a רשות. reshus, It's only five or close. So now
we're no longer dealing with making a רשות היחיד, Reshus Hayachid it's
not wide enough. But what if it is seven and a קצת
k'tzas a little bit or certainly if it's shorter, then it hits
three טפחים, tefachim, it becomes part of the ground and it's an
object in the רשות הרבים reshus harabbim and you're חייב. chayiv. Fine.
But if it is seven and and more than a משהו, mashu,
let's say it's seven and a half, then as soon as it
hits within three, it's like it's already connected to the ground, okay,
because it's within three it's like it's connected to the ground, but
then part of the object is higher than ten טפחים. tefachim. You
see how that works? Is that clear? No?
I'll tell you what.
Look, here's my cup. Let's do it like this. Let's do it
like this. This is the object, okay? If it is less than
six by four... less than six diameter, so it's not four by
four, it's only going to be an object, it's not going to
be a רשות, reshus okay? So if it is just a drop
more than seven, as soon as it gets under three, so you
add the 2.99 and the 7.01,
right? So just just got within the three, right? And now the
whole thing is considered to be in the landing on the ground
because it's within three and it doesn't exceed ten טפחים tefachim because
this is 7.01 and it entered into 2.99, so the entire thing
is ten, it's in רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, you're חייב. chayiv. Yes,
clear? But if it's 7.1,
then as soon as it gets to 2.99,
okay, it's considered on the ground, and you still have a point
whatever it is, .08 or whatever, that's above the ten טפחים. tefachim.
So then you are פטור patur because it is not all in
רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. And then the amazing thing is that then
even as it continues to fall, you remain פטור. patur. That's what
I... since I understand. That's what it says, that since when it
first is considered to have hit רשות הרבים reshus harabbim and come
to a rest, although it's only a virtual rest because of the
principle of לבוד, lavud, it's considered to be not fully in, even
when it becomes fully in, you are פטור. patur. That is the
way that רש"י Rashi explains it. תוספות Tosafos has an alternate explanation.
One minute, תוספות's Tosafos explanation is, let me just double check it.
Oh, all right, I'm
not going to... all
right, I'm not going to get into תוספות Tosafos because it gets
a little too complicated because whatever. תוספות Tosafos says that we're talking
about measuring from the outside, not measuring from the inside, and it
gets more complicated, so we'll leave it with רש"י Rashi for now.
Yes, Michael?
My question is, let's say it's, you know, rotating in the air
and then it actually comes to rest the other way around. But
would you say that since at some point, you know, that you're
saying לבוד lavud is into... like, I don't understand how you can
say a motion is לבוד lavud and connected to the ground.
I understand for a
סוכה, sukkah, you know, if it's a stationary...
I got... I got all the questions. Okay, תוספות Tosafos gives an
alternate explanation, but I for the sake of simplicity I won't go
into it. You might be happy with it.
I'm sorry, but I think it's like seven and a half, not
seven.
Yes, it is. שבע ומשהו. sheva umashu. Yes, I gave the example
of... I really gave the example as not being a half, it's
really anything more than a משהו. mashu. But yes, the גמרא Gemara
says... right. So if it's 7.01
and then it gets into 2.99, okay, then you're חייב. chayiv. Anything
more than that, as soon as it hits 2.99, part of it
is above. So the example was a more dramatic seven and a
half. Correct. תוספות Tosafos has a different explanation. Even according to רש"י,
Rashi, we should note that when it's the base coming to the
ground, we don't do that math because we don't say although we
say לבוד, lavud, we don't, as it were, sort of imagine the
walls extended as you might imagine as it's already on the ground.
But because the floor breaks, we might... but when it's the walls
this way, we imagine the conceptually the walls have extended and it's
already on the ground at the height that it is. תוספות Tosafos
doesn't like that just for the reason... I mean, he has another
explanation in the גמרא, Gemara, but he says we would not extend
a wall unless it was already ten טפחים. tefachim. This wall that's
only seven טפחים, tefachim, we don't extend it to say לבוד. lavud.
So תוספות Tosafos has another explanation. Anyway, that's what we have. Now
the גמרא Gemara continues, it says like this: רב
אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, רב אשי Rav Ashi says, אפילו שבע
ומחצה חייב, afillu sheva umachetza chayiv, even seven and a half you're
חייב. chayiv. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? מחיצות לתוכן עשויות. mechitzos letochan asuyos.
The same way by the floor, we don't extend it, and we
say if it's coming floor first, it's only considered to have landed
when it hits, or even if it's considered לבוד, lavud, we don't
say where it is, we imagine it as if it's on the
ground. Even when it's this way, we're not going to consider these
walls. The walls of a... we might consider it if they're ten
טפחים, tefachim, we might consider it a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid, like
we've been considering it. But if you have walls of a beehive
that are there to serve the stuff on the inside, they're not
there to function as walls, they're there as a vessel, they're there
to contain the stuff that's put in them. In that type of
a case, we don't consider them walls and at least certainly not
at seven טפחים, tefachim, not yet, whatever, an object, a thing, okay?
And therefore, we're not going to extend them conceptually three טפחים tefachim
down. So the same way when it goes this way, you're not
פטור patur when it hits three טפחים tefachim because some. if it
is above, cause we say, you know, the walls of the floor,
if it's on the ground you're חייב. chayav. So even if it's
up here it's חייב. chayav. Then when it's this way as well,
we don't say that even in mid-air it's like the walls that
have already extended to the ground. These are not real walls and
therefore you're חייב chayav when it hits because then it's all within
ten טפחים. tefachim. Okay, was that more or less clear? I'm not
saying that this is a simple issue, but the basic point here
is some fascinating stuff with a little bit of math and this
idea of the beehive according to רש״י, Rashi, the important principle is,
well first of all that the domain of רשות היחיד reshus hayachid
goes by, not by not by area but you need four by
four in each direction. So if it's a circle you need four
times the square root of two. This other interesting concept that
you're
not חייב chayav for throwing a domain, תוספות Tosafot explains it differently
because you end up putting it in a different domain because it
became a different domain, so it landed in its own domain. But
anyway, according to רש״י Rashi you're not חייב chayav for throwing a
domain. Also a very important principle is you're not חייב chayav when
you put something down in רשות הרבים reshut harabim if part of
the height extends beyond higher than ten טפחים. tefachim. So big objects
you'll never be חייב chayav for in a רשות הרבים. reshut harabim.
Okay and then the only debate was what if a little twig
goes above, is that considered like it's going above? What if based
on לבוד lavud principles it's considered to be above before it hits
the ground? Do you say לבוד, lavud, is it a wall, is
it not a wall, right? How about the fact that it's going
to land and when it started it was above ten, but that's
all variations of the point that if it's not fully in רשות
הרבים, reshut harabim, if a little bit extends beyond, you're going to
be exempt. Okay, obviously more to say about that but that's enough
for now. אמר עולא, Amar Ulla, so אמר תשעה Amar tisha now
a more sort of normal case which we've mentioned earlier. אמר תשעה
ברשות הרבים, Amar tisha bereshut harabim, you have a pillar that's nine
טפחים tefachim high in רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. Remember we said that
anything within three טפחים, tefachim, not anything, if it's within three טפחים
tefachim and it is used by the רבים, rabim,
it is, you know, people walk through it and so on, it's
part of the רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, but use is critical. We
also discussed yesterday
holes in walls near רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, the debate of אביי
ורבא, Abaye ve-Rava, are those used enough to be considered to be
part of the רשות הרבים? reshut harabim? By רשות הרבים reshut harabim
as opposed to רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid
use is a central part of the definition. By רשות היחיד reshut
hayachid, it's the structure. So now we're going to ask an interesting
question. Let's say you have something that's used in רשות הרבים reshut
harabim but it's not considered part of the ground. It's a pillar
nine טפחים tefachim high. That will be something that is regularly used,
as we're about to find out the example I gave would be
like in the bathrooms where you have those baby changing tables, right?
Perfectly situated for use for the people, but it's not, you know,
it's not nine, it's not within three טפחים, tefachim, it's not part
of the ground, but it is there and it's made for convenient
use by the people of רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. Is that space
considered רשות הרבים reshut harabim or not? So that's what עולא Ulla
is going to say. אמר תשעה ברשות הרבים, Amar tisha bereshut harabim,
a pillar nine in רשות הרבים reshut harabim ורבים מכתפין עליה verabim
mekatfin aleha and the masses use it to, literally the word like
כתף, katayf, shoulder, to, you know, arrange their packages on, rearrange their
packages. So וזרק ונחה על גבה vezarak venacha al gaba somebody threw
four אמות arba amot and landed on that space or threw from
רשות היחיד reshut hayachid and landed on that space, חייב, chayav, you're
חייב. chayav. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? Why? פחות משלשה מדרס דרסי לה
רבים. pachot mishlosha midras darsi lah rabim. We already established yesterday that
lower than three, unless it's something like a thornbush or excrement, people
will walk on, and if you walk on it that makes it
part of רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, it's used functionally, it serves as
part of the רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. משלשה ועד תשעה mishlosha ve-ad
tisha from three to nine, לא מדרס דרסי לה, lo midras darsi
lah, it's too big to walk on, ולא כתפי מכתפי, velo katfe
mekatfe, but it's not tall enough to use to like as a
changing table. Okay, תשעה tisha at nine טפחים tefachim ורבים מכתפין עלייהו
verabim mekatfin aleihu people use it to change in a what?
Just the right height.
Just the right height, exactly. People use it to arrange their packages
and therefore it's part of a רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. So we
see here a very important principle. Use is really almost the primary
definition for רשות הרבים reshut harabim even though it is not part
of the ground. Three טפחים, tefachim, only under three טפחים tefachim is
structurally part of the ground. It is not part of the ground
since it is in the airspace of רשות הרבים reshut harabim and
since it's used by the רבים, rabim, it has a status of
a רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. Things that are not used by the
רבים, rabim, things between three and nine טפחים, tefachim, will either be
a כרמלית karmelit or מקום פטור. makom patur. כרמלית karmelit if they're
four by four area, מקום פטור makom patur if they're less. But
nine טפחים tefachim because of its use and because it's in the
airspace, that is a רשות הרבים. reshut harabim.
Even above ten טפחים tefachim and the רבים rabim use it?
That wouldn't matter.
No. Right. אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף, Amar lei Abaye le-Rav Yosef,
so right, has to be within the airspace. אביי Abaye said to
רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, גומא מאי? Guma mai? How about if it's
not a pillar, what about if it's a hole in the ground?
Yesterday we spoke about holes in the walls. What about holes in
the ground? Do people maybe put stuff in holes in the ground?
It's much harder to imagine how usable that would be. Hole in
a wall you could understand a little table platform, hole in the
ground is a little harder, but okay, what about hole in the
ground? Would that also be something used by
the
רבים? rabim? Something used only with difficulty is not, does not constitute
for a רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. You might realize that this exactly
parallels the debate of אביי Abaye and רבא Rava yesterday about holes,
holes in the wall. Holes in the wall אביי Abaye says is
a רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, רבא Rava said it is not. So
רבא Rava has a higher criteria for ease of use. For רבא,
Rava, only if it's very high degree of ease of use makes
it a רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. אביי Abaye says even not so
much, even a hole in the ground, even not such much. For
him it's just like his position about a hole in the wall.
That is enough to make it part of a רשות הרבים. reshus
harabim. Now תוספות Tosafot says רש״י Rashi somewhat strangely says we're talking
about a hole exactly the same height or depth, a hole nine
טפחים. tefachim. תוספות Tosafot says no, says for holes, the closer they
are to the ground the more usable they are. It's not like
when it's way down to ten, I don't know what רש״י Rashi
except רש״י Rashi thought maybe it's too close to the ground, other
people will take it, it'll get stepped on. But anyway תוספות Tosafot
says we're talking about pretty much all holes. רש״י Rashi says only
very deep holes, okay, or nine טפחים tefachim deep. Anyway, it's the
exact same debate of אביי Abaye and רבא Rava yesterday about things
that are used, but used with a certain amount of difficulty. איתיביה
Asei רב אדא בר מתנה לרבא. Rav Ada bar Matna le-Rava. So
רב אדא בר מתנה Rav Ada bar Matna asked on רבא: Rava:
הייתה קופה מונחת ברשות הרבים, Haytah kuppa munachat birshus harabim, גבוהה עשרה
ורחבה ארבעה. gevohah asarah u-revachah arba'ah. Let's say you have a basket
in the רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, it's ten טפחים tefachim off the
ground, it's on some type of a pillar, and it's four טפחים
tefachim wide. Then that essentially becomes a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid because
basically we see the base of the pillar, here's your basket, if
it's four by four and it's ten טפחים tefachim off the ground,
somehow we see it like these walls here extend all the way
to the ground, and the inside of the basket becomes a רשות
היחיד reshus hayachid once it's higher than ten טפחים. tefachim. So then,
if that's true...
how big is this, was it ten טפחים? tefachim?
No. But because it's higher than ten טפחים tefachim off the ground,
we imagine that whatever little wall you have here extends to the
ground and becomes a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid because of a conceptual
extending wall.
No matter how high it is?
Yes, as long as it's higher than ten. Okay, so we'll do
with more of that later, but for now we'll accept that,
a point where it becomes like the ridiculous to say.
All right, what can I tell you. Anyway, אין מטלטלין לא מתוכה
לרשות הרבים ולא מרשות הרבים לתוכה. ein mataltelin lo mitochah lereshus harabim
velo mershus harabim letochah. You can't take from the basket into the
public domain or public domain into the basket. It's considered to be
a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid It is a little bit bizarre I
imagine, but I agree, but we're not going to unpack that one
right now. פחות מכאן, Pachas mikan, if it's smaller than that, meaning
it's not four by four or if it's within lower than ten
טפחים, tefachim, then it's just a basket in the רשות הרבים. reshus
harabim. Then מטלטלין, mataltelin, you can take from it into the רשות
הרבים reshus harabim and vice versa. It's just a basket. It's not
a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. וכן בגומא, Ve-chein begummah, and the same
is true with a hole. So מאי לאו אסיפא, mai lav aseifa,
doesn't that mean that if you have a hole in the ground
of a רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, as long as it's not ten
deep and four wide? If you've got a hole that's ten deep
and four wide, it's a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. That's more obvious,
right? It's got the walls and it's ten deep and it's four
by four. But if it's a smaller hole, then it's רשות הרבים
reshus harabim and you can carry from it into the רשות הרבים
reshus harabim and from רשות הרבים reshus harabim into the hole. So
look, this is a proof like אביי. Abaye. A little hole in
רשות הרבים reshus harabim is רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. According to רבא,
Rava, that's not a רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. What would the hole
be? It would be a... if it's bigger than, if it's four
by four, it would be a כרמלית. karmelis. If it's a כרמלית,
karmelis, you can't carry from רשות הרבים reshus harabim into the hole
or vice versa. So here it says if the hole is not
ten by four, you can move from it into the רשות הרבים.
reshus harabim. You see it's a רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. Let's just
see the answer. מאי לאו אסיפא? mai lav aseifa? Does it not
go on the end case, that you can carry from it into
רשות הרבים reshus harabim and vice versa?
לא ארישא. lo, areisha. No. גומא Gummah means if the hole is
ten deep and four by four, it's a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid.
That was the comparison. The ten and four רשות היחיד reshus hayachid.
case. If it's less than that, that we're not making a comparison.
Then maybe it's a כרמלית, karmelis, we're not really necessarily asserting that
it's a רשות הרבים reshus harabim if it's less than that. Yes.
You're חייב chiyaiv to carry over four אמות amos in a רשות
הרבים. reshus harabim.
Right. So you can carry less than four אמות. amos. That's right.
Does that also apply if it's a vertical movement up and down?
No, horizontal. Horizontal, right. That only the four אמות amos is only
horizontal. But then if it's a כרמלית, karmelis, why didn't we say
the same thing about the כוורת? kaveret? What? Why didn't we say
the same thing about the... Oh, רש״י Rashi says, why didn't we
say the same thing about the basket? So that's a good question.
So basically I should make this point, תוספות Tosafot says this already.
We don't consider, we don't consider objects to be רשויות reshuyot except,
well רש״י Rashi said it by the כוורת, kaveret, but we don't
consider them to be a כרמלית. karmelis. When the basket is within
ten טפחים tefachim or the כוורת kaveret is smaller, then it's just
a basket and the כוורת. kaveret. The only time we'll transform an
object like a basket or כוורת kaveret and call it a רשות
reshus, is when it is a real רשות, reshus. רשות היחיד. reshus
hayachid A כרמלית karmelis is not a real רשות. reshus. A כרמלית
karmelis is a rabbinic רשות. Yes.
It just strikes me as we read all these technical measurements and
sizes and
spaces, that we can be so absorbed in this technicality, how
do...
But we
do and
how maybe we're not learning תורה *Torah* the right way. Okay, איתיבי
*Esvei*. Now here is another question that אביי Abaye, *Abaye* is going
to be challenged at, that holes should be a רשות הרבים reshut
harabim. *reshus harabim*. Top of ח עמוד ב *ches amud beis*. המניח
עירובו בבור *Hamaniach eruvo bebor* למעלה מעשרה טפחים tefachim *lemala measara tefachim*.
So this is another classic עירובין eiruvin, *eruvin* discussion. The idea of
an עירוב eiruv. *eruv*, not עירוב eruv, חצרות *eruv chatzeros*, of coming
together in a courtyard so that the courtyard can be carried in,
but the idea of עירוב תחומין *eruv techumin*. You're not allowed to
go, maybe biblical, maybe rabbinic, more than 2,000 אמות amot *amos*, like
about 2,000 kilometers or so, outside of, three-sevenths of a mile outside
of city limits. Unless
you
make an עירוב *eruv*, you put some food there,
and that food is representative as if you began שבת *Shabbos* where
the food was and then you can go 2,000 אמות amot *amos*
from where the food is placed. So if you want to go
outside a city limit, the way you deal with it is you
put food outside and as long as that space, you know, if
here's your city,
this is your city
and this is your 2,000 אמות amot, *amos* limit, okay? So if
you start שבת *Shabbos* in the city, you can only go up
to 2,000 אמות amot *amos*. However, if you put your food right
at the edge of the 2,000 אמות amot *amos*, then because the
2,000 אמות *amos* overlaps into the city, you can go throughout the
entire city because there's a little bit that overlaps, you see how
it overlaps? And because you started at this point and not at
this point, you can also go 2,000 אמות *amos* in that direction.
So nobody steals your food.
What? Unless somebody does steal your food. Now talking about which, the
food has to be there, you are correct, when שבת *Shabbos* begins.
Not only that, because it is like you have started שבת *Shabbos*
there, you have to be able in theory, were you there, to
access and eat the food. Okay? If you cannot access and eat
the food, it's not like you began שבת *Shabbos* there. So here's
the scenario. You said I'm going to begin my שבת *Shabbos* right
there on that street, now outside of the city. Now where was
your food? Your food was המניח עירובו בבור *hamaniach eruvo bebor*. You
put your food into a well. Now you got a problem because
how can you be standing in the street where you conceptually said
you're starting your שבת *Shabbos* and getting to your food which is
in the בור *bor* which is in רשות היחיד reshus hayachid. *reshus
hayachid* and you're in רשות הרבים reshut harabim. *reshus harabim*? So you
got a little bit of a problem. So here it was then:
למעלה מעשרה טפחים tefachim *lemala measara tefachim*, if the pit, if the
food, it sounds like the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will say if the
pit is not as deep as ten טפחים tefachim *tefachim*, so the
pit is just a
כרמלית karmelit *karmelis*, then עירובו עירוב *eruvo eruv*, then it's okay, then
in theory you could access the food. למטה מעשרה טפחים tefachim *lemata
measara tefachim*, if it's deeper than ten טפחים *tefachim*, so it's in
a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid *reshus hayachid*, אין עירובו עירוב *ein eruvo
eruv*, so you can't be in the רשות הרבים reshut harabim. *reshus
harabim* and your food be in a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid. *reshus
hayachid* and it doesn't count. So the גמרא Gemara's *Gemara* says like
this: היכי דמי *Heichi dami*? What's the case? אילימא בבור דאית ביה
עשרה *Elima bebor deis bei asara*, if in both cases the pit
has is ten טפחים *tefachim* deep and it's a רשות היחיד reshut
hayachid. *reshus hayachid*, so what does it mean higher or lower? It
means where is the food in the pit? ולמעלה *Ulemala* when it
says higher than ten, דלייה ואותביה *delayei veosvei*, the food is raised
up and it's high up in the pit, it's closer to the
ground level. ולמטה *Ulemata* when it says lower, אחתי ואותביה *achteia veosvei*,
you placed it lower down, which is what it sounds like. It
sounds like the pit is very deep and how high or low
is the food. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says that can't be the
case because if the pit is deep and it's ten טפחים *tefachim*,
even if the food is close to the ground level, it's still
in a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid, *reshus hayachid*, right? You get that?
I mean if it's, if the pit is deep, even if it's
only a foot away from you, an inch away from you, it's
in a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid. *reshus hayachid*. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says that that can't be. So it says מה לי למעלה
מה לי למטה *ma li lemala ma li lemata*? What do I
care where the food is whether it's high or low? הוא במקום
אחד ועירובו במקום אחר *Hu bemakom echad veeruvo bemakom acher*. You're in
one place, רשות הרבים reshut harabim *reshus harabim*, and the food is
in a halakhically different domain that you can't access to get the,
you know, for the food. It's in a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid.
*reshus hayachid*. אלא לאו ela lav, *Ela lav*, we don't mean where
is the food, we mean how high is the, deep is the
well. בבור דלית ביה עשרה *Bebor deleis bei asara*. We mean if
the well is less than ten, you're okay, the food is not
in רשות היחיד reshut hayachid? *reshus hayachid*. If the בור *bor*, if
the pit is deeper than ten, you got a problem, the food
is in a רשות היחיד *reshus hayachid*. Now the גמרא *Gemara* says
okay, but why is it okay if the, if the well is
less than ten? It's still in a כרמלית Carmelit. *karmelis*. You're in
רשות הרבים reshut harabim *reshus harabim*. You're not able to carry food
from the כרמלית *karmelis* to where you are. So even if the
pit is less than ten, why is it okay? וקתני עירובו עירוב
*Ukatani eruvo eruv*. We see it says that it works. אלמא *Alma*,
so you see, תשמיש על ידי הדחק al yedei hadachak, שמיה תשמיש
*tashmish al yedei hadachak shmei tashmish*. So even though you can only
use this well with a little bit of difficulty, this pit, it's
considered to be a genuine part of רשות הרבים reshut harabim? *reshus
harabim*. So the argument here is, here you got food in a
pit, it's less than ten טפחים *tefachim* and the... And the ברייתא
Beraita *braita* is implicitly saying you can take the food from the
pit and eat it in the רשות הרבים reshut harabim. *Reshut HaRabbim*.
So look, that must mean that the pit is considered a רשות
הרבים reshut harabim, *Reshut HaRabbim*, like אביי *Abaye*, that even holes in
the ground are רשות הרבים reshut harabim, *Reshut HaRabbim*, because if it's
a כרמלית *karmelit* like רבא Rava's *Rava* says, how can you take
the food out of the pit and eat it in the רשות
הרבים reshut harabim. *Reshut HaRabbim*? What did he want to say here?
He has to leave the food before שבת *Shabbat*.
Before שבת *Shabbat* and
the next day they get it.
He doesn't have to do anything with it the next day. It
just has to be there throughout
בין השמשות *bein ha-shmashot*. Right. It has to be put there before
sunset and be there throughout the entire בין השמשות *bein ha-shmashot*. Whether
he eats it or not, that doesn't matter.
He just has to be מניח *mani'ach* this סעודה *se'udah*.
I know, it's true. So that is an issue. Okay. So now
the גמרא *Gemara* says: Oh, so you see that even though you
can only use it with difficulty, it's considered use and it's considered
רשות הרבים reshut harabim *Reshut HaRabbim*. So that's a challenge to רבא
Rava's *Rava*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says: זימנין משני ליה *Zimnin meshani
lei* sometimes he said הוא ועירובו בכרמלית *hu ve-eruvo be-karmelit*. All right,
it says that he wanted to start your שבת *Shabbat* in the
רשות הרבים reshut harabim *Reshut HaRabbim*, but we don't really mean רשות
הרבים reshut harabim *Reshut HaRabbim*. We meant the space near the well
was a כרמלית *karmelit*. ואמאי קרי ליה רשות הרבים reshut harabim. *Ve-amai
kari lei Reshut HaRabbim*? So why call it רשות הרבים reshut harabim,
*Reshut HaRabbim*? משום דלאו רשות היחיד *Mishum de-lav reshut ha-yachid*. It meant
a non-רשות היחיד *reshut ha-yachid*. We had an answer like that before,
except the reverse. We called something רשות היחיד *reshut ha-yachid* which really
was a כרמלית *karmelit* but it wasn't a רשות הרבים reshut harabim,
*Reshut HaRabbim*. Okay, so that's a weak answer. רשות הרבים reshut harabim,
*Reshut HaRabbim* doesn't really mean it. וזימנין משני ליה *Ve-zimnin meshani lei*,
sometimes he gave and this seemed to be a better answer. הוא
ברשות הרבים harabim, ועירובו בכרמלית *Hu be-reshut ha-rabbim ve-eruvo be-karmelit*. You know
what? You're right. I concede that it's רשות הרבים reshut harabim? *Reshut
HaRabbim*, but he's in a רשות הרבים reshut harabim, *Reshut HaRabbim* and
I will stay with my position that I've said until now, the
pit is a כרמלית *karmelit* and nevertheless it still works. You can
be in a רשות הרבים reshut harabim *Reshut HaRabbim* and your food
in a כרמלית *karmelit* and that counts as an עירוב *eruv*. Why?
You're not allowed... no, but you're not allowed to take from a
כרמלית *karmelit* to רשות הרבים reshut harabim *Reshut HaRabbim*. דרבי *De-Rabbi*, because
it's the position of רבי *Rabbi*. דאמר *De-amar*, and this is the
position in עירובין *Eruvin* that he says in a few places: כל
דבר שהוא משום שבות לא lo, גזרו עליו בין השמשות *Kol davar
she-hu mishum shevut lo gazru alav bein ha-shmashot*. That it's a general
position and it applies specifically to עירוב *eruv* as well. Very important
on הלכות שבת *hilchot Shabbat*. Things that are rabbinic don't apply בין
השמשות *bein ha-shmashot*. Now, don't apply
when it's from sunset before the stars come out, because that's a
rabbinic time period, so rabbinic restrictions don't apply. Now if you really
apply this across the board, you can imagine what the implications would
be. Like, okay great, so therefore let's say we'll assume that electricity
without lights is a דרבנן Derabbanan *derabbanan*, so I can still be
watching TV after sunset until it gets to be forty-five minutes after
sunset on Friday night. So is that really true that we say
that? So there's two qualifications afterwards that the פוסקים *poskim* say.
Hillel or Shamai, right?
Well, no, so there's two qualifications. One is, one qualification is that
it has to be some type of a צורך מצוה *tzorech mitzvah*,
some type of a justifiable purpose. Can't be just סתם *stam* that
you want to do מלאכה *melacha* afterwards. The other issue, do you
want to do a דרבנן Derabbanan *derabbanan*? The other issue is that
it's only if you have not been מקבל שבת *mekabel Shabbat*. So
it's only if you haven't lit candles or said קבלת שבת *kabbalat
Shabbat* because once you've done that you've defined that it's already שבת
*Shabbat*. But this can come up
sometimes where somebody really is running late in the car in the
middle of the they're like then we would allow like they're caught
outside of they're stuck on the highway calling a taxi, other types
of things where it's important to know that under certain circumstances דרבנן
*derabbanan's* don't apply in בין השמשות *bein ha-shmashot*. How is it relevant
here? It's particularly relevant here because when your עירוב *eruv* has to
be edible is during the period of בין השמשות *bein ha-shmashot*. And
we're assuming there's a general debate of can you make an עירוב
*eruv* for any purpose to go outside of city limits or only
for a צורך מצוה *tzorech mitzvah*. So we might be assuming that
it's a צורך מצוה *tzorech mitzvah*. Anyway, but since your עירוב *eruv*
only has to be edible בין השמשות *bein ha-shmashot*, so if you
say you can do דרבנן *derabbanan's* בין השמשות *bein ha-shmashot*, so it's
considered edible even if it's in a כרמלית *karmelit*. Is that clear?
Meaning you're in a רשות הרבים reshut harabim, *Reshut HaRabbim*, it's in
a כרמלית *karmelit*, the only way you would be able to eat
it is by transgressing a דרבנן *derabbanan*. But that's okay for an
עירוב *eruv* even if you had to transgress a דרבנן *derabbanan* because
we're going according to רבי *Rabbi* that says when you need to
during בין השמשות *bein ha-shmashot*, which is the time period that matters,
you can transgress a דרבנן *derabbanan*. Okay, so therefore it works. It's
not a proof that the hole was רשות הרבים reshut harabim *Reshut
HaRabbim*, the hole could be a כרמלית *karmelit*. Okay.
You have to have the food throughout all שבת *Shabbat*?
No, just when שבת *Shabbat* begins. The minute שבת *Shabbat* begins. So
it's only for the period of בין השמשות *bein ha-shmashot*. Okay. ולא
תימא v'lo teima *Ve-lo teima*, now the גמרא *Gemara* says: so that
was it, but now going back to אביי *Abaye*, it says ולא
תימא דכי קמדחינא לך, אלא ela, דווקא קאמינא לך *Ve-lo teima de-chi
kamidachina lach, ela davka kamina lach*. Don't say it sounds like it's
going on רבא Rava *Rava's* point but it really is going back
to אביי *Abaye*. It says אביי *Abaye* 'don't say I'm just pushing
you away', I am being very serious about the point. That's funny,
that's normally a phrase used after responding to an answer, but we'll
see as it continues. It's basically אביי *Abaye's* point which is 'I
am being very serious' that even if you can only use it
על ידי דחק *al yedei dechak* it has a full status of
a...
oh, wait, no, no, no. I'm sorry, no, no, no, I'm sorry,
I'm sorry. It is רבא's Rava point. I'm sorry, it is רבא's
Rava's point, I'm sorry. It is רבא's Rava's point, but still not
going back to his answer here about עירוב. But okay, so yes,
but the just the general pattern. ולא תימא דחויי קמדחינא לך, v'lo
teima d'chuyei k'mad'china lach, I'm not just pushing you away, you know,
I am sort of getting rid of this problem here about the
כרמלית and the עירובין, but it's not for, but I really have
back-up is what he's going to be saying. While this answer sounds
like just a דחוי dichui like I'm just swatting it away and
you know you really have you think you've really proven your point.
I want to tell you, says רבא to אביי, that I really
do have serious backing to my position that these holes do not
count as a רשות הרבים. reshut harabim, Let's see why. ולא תימא
so again, it is רבא talking. ולא תימא דחויי קמדחינא לך, v'lo
teima d'chuyei k'mad'china lach, don't say I'm just sort of like pushing
you away that my position is a weak one, אלא דוקא קאמינא
לך. ela davka ka'amina lach. I am telling you a real serious
position that these holes do not count as a רשות הרבים. reshut
harabim Why? דתנן. d'tnan. Here's a parallel משנה. mishnah. היה רקק מים
ורשות הרבים מהלכת בו. haya rekek mayim u'reshut harabim mahalachet bo. You
have a pond of water, a puddle of water, maybe puddle, whatever.
What's... what? רקק? rekek?
רקיקה rekika is like spit.
Right. ויש v'yesh some type of a dirty puddle of water that
goes across the רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. But people just, but the
path goes through it and people continue to walk through it. הזורק
לתוכה ארבע אמות חייב. hazorek l'tocha arba amot chayav. It still has
the status of רשות הרבים reshut harabim, as long as people don't
avoid it, they continue to walk through this puddle, it still has
the status of רשות הרבים reshut harabim, and you throw four אמות
you're חייב. chayav. וכמה הוא רקק מים? v'kama hu rekek mayim? How
big does it is it until, you know, that still considered part
of the רשות הרבים? reshut harabim It's not considered some separate space.
פחות מעשרה טפחים. pachot m'asara tefachim. Less than ten טפחים deep. If
it's more than ten טפחים deep, if it's more than ten טפחים
deep, then it's going to be its own domain, it's going to
be רשות היחיד maybe, it's not going to be part of the
רשות הרבים. reshut harabim Okay, so
okay. Now, ורקק מים v'rekek mayim and then it repeats itself.
ורקק מים ורשות הרבים מהלכת בו v'rekek mayim u'reshut harabim mahalachet bo
and by the way, a puddle of water that people walk through
it, הזורק לתוכה ארבע אמות חייב. hazorek l'tocha arba amot chayav. If
you throw four אמות you're חייב. chayav. So it said the exact
same thing beginning and end. Why did it repeat itself? So this
is רבא's question. בשלמא רקק רקק תרי זימני, bishlama rekek rekek trei
zimnei, I understand why it had to say twice, say puddle of
water, puddle of water, repeat itself, talk about the puddle because there
are two types of scenarios. חד בימות החמה וחד בימות הגשמים. chad
biyemot hachama v'chad biyemot hageshamim. You could imagine puddles in the rainy
season and in the summer season. And maybe they would have a
different status. Why would they have a different status? צריכא, tzricha, you
need to tell me both. אי אשמעינן בימות החמה, ei ashmi'inan biyemot
hachama, had he told me puddles in the summertime are considered to
be part of the רשות הרבים, דעבידי אינשי דקרי נפשייהו, d'avidi inshi
d'kari nafshaihu, people sometimes, especially if you're a small kid, like to
walk through the puddles to cool off. So there I understand that
it's considered something that's used. אבל בימות הגשמים, aval biyemot hageshamim, in
the rainy period, אימא לא, eima lo, then maybe people don't walk
through it and maybe there what are you doing when it's raining?
You try to avoid the big puddle. It's looking exactly. All right,
so anyway, so maybe therefore it's not. אימא לא. eima lo. ואי
אשמעינן בימות הגשמים, v'ei ashmi'inan biyemot hageshamim, if you said puddles in
the rainy season are part of the רשות הרבים, אגב דמיטנפי, agav
d'mitnafei, since anyway you're dirty, מיקרי ונחתי, mikri v'nachti, so you don't
mind, so you walk through the puddle. אבל בימות החמה, aval biyemot
hachama, in the summer, לא, you're going to avoid the puddle. צריכא.
tzricha. So you have to tell me puddle twice to tell me
whatever the scenario is, people will walk through puddles and not that
it's necessarily their ideal, but they'll be prepared to walk through puddles
and it's part of the רשות הרבים.
It says between summer and winter, בין בימות החמה בין בימות הגשמים.
bein biyemot hachama bein biyemot hageshamim.
All right, fine, but we'll it doesn't okay. But we have our
way of dealing with this. אלא, that I get, why it had
to say puddle. הילוך תרי זימני למה לי? hiluch trei zimnei lama
li? Why did it have to say twice, a puddle that the
רשות הרבים goes through? A puddle the רשות הרבים goes through? Why
do you have to twice say that the רשות הרבים goes through?
Again, that's clear from context. אלא לאו, it must be it's emphasizing
people walk through it to make a point. שמע מינה אלא לאו
שמע מינה הילוך על ידי הדחק שמי הילוך. shma mina ela lav
shma mina hiluch al yedei hadachak shmei hiluch. If you walk through
something even if it's not the most convenient, that's considered still that
you're going through it and it's part of the רשות הרבים. תשמיש
על ידי הדחק לא שמי תשמיש. tashmish al yedei hadachak lo shmei
tashmish. If it's some use that isn't walking, some other use like
putting your objects there, like in a hole, you don't walk in
the hole, you're using it for putting your objects, then when it's
use על ידי הדחק, al yedei hadachak, לא שמי תשמיש, lo shmei
tashmish, that is not considered a real use. שמע מינה. shma mina.
And the גמרא feels that that is a good proof. Again, it's
a very big thing to read into an extra word, but this
is a nice articulation of רבא's position. Because remember, we said the
other day that by רשות הרבים, and again I said today, the
central definition is usage. Okay, so you get the main רשות הרבים,
it's a major thoroughfare. But then your question is all these things
which are holes and pillars and holes in the walls and the
edges of רשות הרבים, to what degree are they part or not
part of רשות הרבים? So if they're a major use like as
the major רשות הרבים, it goes without a question. But the גמרא's
whole questions were about things that were על ידי הדחק, little alleyways,
little קרן זוית, keren zavit, little holes, things like that. little puddles,
things that are not as much a regular part of the usage
but will be used. And רבא *Rava* has a nice articulation of
a difference. He says
primarily רשות הרבים *reshus harabbim* is about, definitely the street רשות הרבים
*reshus harabbim* as opposed to the square, is about walking, moving, traveling.
So the parts of it that are used for traveling are more
ready to be considered a part of the רשות הרבים *reshus harabbim*
even if it's only הילוך על ידי הדחק *hiloch al yedei hadachak*,
even if it's only with a certain degree of, you know, discomfort
or not, not so easy. But the parts of it that aren't
for traveling, that are just for use, only if it's a very
easy use. So the pillar like we were talking about, like the
changing table, that is very easy use, that is part of רשות
הרבים *reshus harabbim*. But other things like holes in walls and holes
in grounds, that's different. That is not for walking, it's for use,
but the use is not so convenient, that is not. אביי *Abaye*
doesn't make that distinction, but רבא *Rava* says there's a difference between
use of walking which is the primary function of רשות הרבים *reshus
harabbim* and more things are part of it, other types of usage
is a more of a secondary and only things that are very
convenient use. And that's רבא *Rava*.
And strangely, they don't refer to a puddle, they, which makes me
very confused, they refer to a swamp. Now a swamp to me
is a huge thing, whereas a puddle is a small.
Yeah, I translated it as puddle.
I mean, I'm more, not worried about the word so much as
what the meaning is.
A swamp, I mean it could be either way, as long as
it's a space that you'll go walk through, it's still part of
רשות הרבים *reshus harabbim*. If you, even if you'll only walk through
it, you know, even if it's not so convenient, but you'll be
prepared to walk through it. If it's a place that you, you
know, circumnavigate, that you move around, then it's not. And that's the
basic rule like the גמרא *Gemara* before, excrement and thorn bushes, the
things you avoid are not רשות הרבים *reshus harabbim*, the things you'll
be prepared to walk through, even though you ideally wouldn't walk through
excrement or thorn bushes, but if you'll do it if you have
to, then it is part of רשות הרבים *reshus harabbim*. But again,
with a greater inclusion of places that are walked through as opposed
to places that are used but used with less convenience. Okay so
let's now see the next סוגיא *sugya*. אמר רב יהודה *Amar Rav
Yehuda*, האי זרזא דקני *hai zarza de'kanei*. Now this is extremely important
for, as you'll immediately realize, a very common carrying question that comes
up. If you've got a bundle of reeds, okay? Let's imagine, yeah,
I guess for סכך *s'chach*, let's say here, this is my bundle
of reeds just because it's tall, but it's obviously thicker but that's
not relevant. And you've got this bundle of reeds in your רשות
הרבים *reshus harabbim*. רמא וזקפיה *rama v'zakfeih*, you throw it and stand
it up, רמא וזקפיה *rama v'zakfeih*, you throw it and stand it
up, לא מיחייב *lo mechayeiv*, you don't transgress, עד דעקר ליה *ad
d'akar leih*, until you pick it up. Which means if
this is, let's say five אמות *amos* tall, okay? And I'm חייב
chayav. *chayav* for carrying four אמות *amos* in רשות הרבים *reshus harabbim*.
Watch how I'm going to carry it through רשות הרבים *reshus harabbim*.
Through that, now why am I פטור patur *patur*? Because I put
it here out of four אמות *amos*, but while part of it
is out of four אמות *amos*, part of it is still within.
It's not all together, and it's come to rest. Okay? So I've
done step one and now the מלאכה *melacha* has been broken. It's
not continuous. Now I do step two and bring the other part
of it out of the original four אמות *amos*, but that's a
different act than bringing the first part out.
Now can you just imagine someone who's not Jewish watching this thing
go on and say, these people are nuts.
What about, if you hand it to somebody else? Well, that's like
the גמרא *Gemara*, the גמרא *Gemara* actually says in a different context,
if you do פחות פחות מארבע אמות *pachus pachus me'arba amos*, you
know, multiple little things, each one less than four, you also don't
transgress biblically. Doesn't mean it's rabbinically allowed, but rabbinically you don't because
as I said, now, you know, each one act isn't מחייב *mechayeiv*
you because part of it is left behind. The second act isn't
מחייב *mechayeiv* you because your first act already stopped because it came
to rest. Now, תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says that is different than, and
here's the question that comes up, a baby carriage. If you do
not have an עירוב *eruv*, are you חייב chayav. *chayav* for a
baby carriage? You never pick it up, you just roll it. So
תוספות *Tosafot* says there's another question about this which is besides that
it came into, it was separate acts, how about the fact that
you never fully lifted the whole thing off the ground? Is that,
are you, is that considered an עקירה *akirah* or not? So there's
another גמרא *Gemara* in כתובות *Kesubos* that says you do not have
to lift it off the ground to be an עקירה *akirah*. The
גמרא *Gemara* talks about picking up, let's say, a wallet is the
case there, and dragging it out like this. And when you go
from רשות הרבים *reshus harabbim* to רשות היחיד *reshus hayachid*, you're חייב
chayav, *chayav*. You don't have to lift it off the ground as
long as you've removed it from its place. So the problem here
is not that it wasn't lifted from the ground, the issue here
was that it came to rest. And therefore תוספות *Tosafot* says a
baby carriage, it doesn't say baby carriage, it says a barrel, but
if you've got a baby
carriage, I'm liable something to throw here other than my trench coat,
which is of course too wet, whatever, just use this. You've got
this, okay, so this never stopped. And since it never stopped, it
started here and you're going here and it's outside four אמות and
you stop here, that's not like our case of separate acts. This
is one continuous act and you're חייב. And even though you didn't
lift it off, it's like dragging it out and you're חייב. However,
he says, if you took a box, right, and you used the
box, if you had like a, if you had like a, I'm
remembering there's some Far Side, I think, that had like a, like
you know, early cavemen when they're like stages in development of the
wheel, and one of the wheels was like, you know, it was
a square. So if you had, so if you had a, but
I wonder at what stage does it become, does it become continuous?
Like say you had like a, like an octagon or something? But
anyway, if you were doing this, you know, a wheel that was
square, then you'd be פטור patur. because at each stage, if you,
if it was smaller than four אמות, each step would be less
than four אמות and you'd be פטור. If it was a thing
that was bigger than four אמות like our things, then fine, you
went outside, but still you stopped and you didn't have the whole
thing outside.
Well, see you didn't stop, you're still doing it like fast.
It doesn't matter if it's, so that's an interesting question, like is
it about the fact that it's flat? If you did it so
quickly that it was continuous, presumably if it was so quickly that
it was fluid, you would be, you would be חייב, but exactly
where you draw the line is not clear. Now תוספות does say,
he raises a good question which he doesn't fully answer, which is:
Remember the גמרא said that when you stop to switch shoulders, לכתפיה,
le-katveih, that's not considered stopping because you just stopped to readjust. So
the, you could actually say that in this case, even though you're
stopping, why does it consider stopping? It's just a momentary stop that
you need in order to move on. So he raises that parallel
without exactly explaining the difference.
Does anyone explain it?
Because I'm not sure.
Yes, so this could be very practical so you're at a building
site, you don't want to
screw your...
up. No, the more practical question is the baby carriage, because in
places without an עירוב, under certain circumstances you have to ask like,
you know, can
you do a דרבנן of a דרבנן במקום מצווה bimkom mitzvah and
so on. And a lot of questions come up with babies, but
the, no, the carriage is different because it's a circle, it does
not have this leniency. It's considered to be, it's only here because
it has these momentary stops.
So if you don't stop with your baby carriage, you're okay?
Well, okay, that would be, if you didn't stop it would not
be a דאורייתא, De'oraita, and then again, so then that raises certain
possibilities. But you have to be able to anticipate taking it all
the way without stopping once or whatever. Okay, so let's take a
look. אמר מר. Amar Mar. Now, back to, back to the ברייתא
about the רשויות. reshuyot. Okay, so let's take a look. Okay, so
that was a lot of fun, but now we get back to
defining the רשויות reshuyot and we are to this balcony or ledge.
אמר מר, Amar Mar,
אדם עומד על האיסקופא, Adam omed al ha-iskofah, you can stand on
the ledge. This is a ledge that presumably overhangs רשות הרבים from
the רשות היחיד. The ledge itself is not four by four טפחים
wide, so it's a מקום פטור. makom patur. It's this free zone.
And a person can be standing on this
ledge, נוטל מבעל הבית ונותן לו. notel mi-baal habayit ve-noten lo. Take
an object from the person in the house and give an object
to the person in the house, because it's a מקום פטור, makom
patur, it's not four by
four, so you can transfer something into it and take something out
of it into a רשות היחיד. Also
and then נוטל מן העני ונותן לו. notel min he-ani ve-noten lo.
You can take something from the עני ani who's in the רשות
הרבים and give something to the עני. ani. So you can use
this space, this מקום פטור, makom patur, to go from it to
a רשות הרבים, from it to רשות היחיד, and vice-versa. So the
גמרא says: האי איסקופא מאי? Hai iskofah mai? What is the story
with this ledge? Where is it? Where is it so ledged in?
אילימא איסקופא רשות הרבים, Ilima iskofah reshut harabim, if it's a ledge
in the רשות הרבים and it's assuming here that it makes, it
would be considered part of the רשות הרבים, meaning it's working out
why this is a מקום פטור, makom patur, that נוטל מבעל הבית,
notel mi-baal habayit, how can you take something from the person in
the house and put it on the ledge? המעביר מרשות היחיד לרשות
הרבים. Ha-mavvir me-reshut hayachid le-reshut harabim. If it's in the רשות הרבים
and it's used by the people of the הרבים, then presumably it
is a רשות הרבים. Why should you be allowed to put something
from the house on the ledge? אלא איסקופא רשות היחיד. Ela iskofah
reshut hayachid. Rather then it's a ledge, again it could mean the
ledge, it could mean a threshold, anyway, it's a ledge that's part
of the רשות היחיד. So then נוטל מן העני? notel min he-ani?
So why can you take something from the עני ani outside of
the רשות הרבים, in the רשות הרבים, and put it on the
ledge? המעביר מרשות הרבים לרשות היחיד. Ha-mavvir me-reshut harabim le-reshut hayachid. You're
bringing it into a private domain. Meaning it's trying to figure out
what we've been saying all along, that it's a מקום פטור, makom
patur, but why? What's the scenario that it is, it's considered its
own domain? אלא איסקופא כרמלית. Ela iskofah carmelit. Okay, so you'll say,
okay, no, no, the ledge is neither רשות הרבים nor רשות היחיד.
So until now, what's the alternative to רשות הרבים or רשות היחיד?
כרמלית. Maybe again it's four by four, it's its own domain, whatever
it is, it's higher than, whatever it is. Okay, but it's still
rabbinically forbidden. נוטל ונותן לכתחילה? notel ve-noten le-chatchilah? You're telling me you
can put... Can put from there into רשות הרבים *reshus harabim* and
רשות היחיד *reshus hayachid* לכתחילה *l'chatchilah*, like it's permissible? סוף סוף איסורא
מיהא איכא *Sof sof issura miha ika*. It's still rabbinically forbidden, it's
a כרמלית *karmelis*. אלא איסקופא מקום פטור בעלמא הוא *Ella iskoppa makom
p'tur b'alma hu*. It comes to the realization that this is a
fourth domain, a free zone, which is מקום פטור *makom p'tur*, a
place of exemption. Not just פטור *p'tur* usually means you're forbidden but
exempt, here really means it's a free zone like free parking. Okay?
And they're literally parking, you can park stuff there. Okay? And therefore
you can, it's permitted even דרבנן *d'rabbanan*. What are the parameters it
needs to be that? כגון דלית ביה ארבעה על ארבעה *Kegon d'leis
bei arba al arba*. It's not four by four טפחים *tefachim* wide.
Anything four by four טפחים *tefachim* is the, has a status of
a רשות *reshus*. It's either a רשות היחיד *reshus hayachid* or it's
a כרמלית *karmelis*. It has a big enough space to be considered
a רשות *reshus*. Something less than four by four טפחים *tefachim*, like
less than a foot by a foot, is like insignificant. It's not
even really in a space. The same way you need to put
an object down on four by four to be חייב *chayav*, as
a space it doesn't consider it a domain less than four by
four. Therefore it's like a non-domain. It's
more than, it's like a permissible domain, it's almost like it's a
non-domain. It's less than four by four and
right, that's rabbinic, that it shouldn't lead to something else. But as
a domain, it's a non-domain and you're totally okay. Now again, if
it's in רשות הרבים *reshus harabim* and used by the רבים *rabim*,
like it's this changing table, it sits then it becomes part of
the רשות הרבים *reshus harabim*. Okay? But if it's, and if it's
in רשות היחיד *reshus hayachid*, then because it's between the walls it's
part of the רשות היחיד *reshus hayachid*. But the scenario would be
it's not used by the רבים *rabim* or it is higher than
ten טפחים *tefachim* from the רשות הרבים *reshus harabim*. In those cases
it is a מקום פטור *makom p'tur*. וכי הא *V'chi ha*, we'll
give one example and end with this for today, וכי אתא רב
דימי *V'chi asa Rav Dimi*, when Rav Dimi came, אמר רבי יוחנן
*Amar Rabbi Yochanan*, he said in the name of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan*, מקום שאין בו ארבעה על ארבעה טפחים *Makom she-ein bo arba
al arba tefachim*, if it doesn't have four by four טפחים *tefachim*,
מותר לבני רשות היחיד ולבני רשות הרבים לכתף עליו *mutar livnei reshus
hayachid u-livnei reshus harabim l'chasef alav*. Both the people from the public
domain and the private domain can use it to put down their
objects. It is a non-domain, a free domain, it is okay. ובלבד
שלא יחליפו *U-bilvad she-lo yachalifu*. But don't use it as a way
of getting from one to the other. You can go from רשות
הרבים *reshus harabim* to it and from it to רשות הרבים *reshus
harabim*, from רשות היחיד *reshus hayachid* to it and it to רשות
היחיד *reshus hayachid*, but don't use it as a step, as a
stopping zone and then eventually go רשות הרבים *reshus harabim*, מקום פטור
*makom p'tur*, רשות היחיד *reshus hayachid*. Because if you do that, next
thing you know you'll be going straight from רשות הרבים *reshus harabim*
to a רשות היחיד *reshus hayachid*. And that is the next line
in the תוספתא *Tosefta* and we'll just read that, no we won't
read that, we will end with that for today.